<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Random Determinism</title>
    <link>https://adityam.github.io/context-blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Random Determinism</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2020 17:12:21 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://adityam.github.io/context-blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>t-vim: A tale of two editors</title>
      <link>https://adityam.github.io/context-blog/post/vim-vs-neovim/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2020 17:12:21 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adityam.github.io/context-blog/post/vim-vs-neovim/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since I am looking at merging a few pull requests for &lt;code&gt;t-vim&lt;/code&gt;, I thought that
this will also be a good time to implement a simple feature that was on hold
for a while: the ability to use the module with &lt;a href=&#34;https://neovim.io/&#34;&gt;Neovim&lt;/a&gt; instead of &lt;code&gt;vim&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New escape mechanism for t-vim</title>
      <link>https://adityam.github.io/context-blog/post/vim-btex-etex-escape/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2020 01:08:56 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adityam.github.io/context-blog/post/vim-btex-etex-escape/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/adityam/filter/blob/master/vim-README.md&#34;&gt;t-vim&lt;/a&gt; module has been on a maintenance only mode for while, so I am
happy to announce a release which adds a new feature: a new method to escape
to TeX using &lt;code&gt;/BTEX&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;/ETEX&lt;/code&gt; tags.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Formatting numbers in Lua</title>
      <link>https://adityam.github.io/context-blog/post/formatting-numbers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adityam.github.io/context-blog/post/formatting-numbers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I often use Lua to generate solution for homework assignments. Ideally, I want
the solution to look exactly how it would look if it were written by hand. But
this can be tricker than it appears at first glance. In this post, I&amp;rsquo;ll
explain the issue and how I solve it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A new key-value interface for Metapost</title>
      <link>https://adityam.github.io/context-blog/post/new-metafun-interface/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adityam.github.io/context-blog/post/new-metafun-interface/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, Hans &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mail-archive.com/ntg-context@ntg.nl/msg91818.html&#34;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; a new key-value driven interface for MetaFun and
posted a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pragma-ade.com/general/magazines/mag-1104-mkiv.pdf&#34;&gt;MyWay document&lt;/a&gt; illustrating its use. In this post, I am going to
present an example of how to use this interface.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Designing cover page for an exam</title>
      <link>https://adityam.github.io/context-blog/post/exam-coverpage/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adityam.github.io/context-blog/post/exam-coverpage/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our university has a specific style that courses need to use as a cover page
for exams, shown below. They circulate a Word template at the beginning of
each term. Since I typeset my exams in ConTeXt, I decided to translate this
cover page template to ConTeXt as well. In this post, I&amp;rsquo;ll explain how I went
about doing this translation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seamlessly switching between different context versions</title>
      <link>https://adityam.github.io/context-blog/post/setuptex/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adityam.github.io/context-blog/post/setuptex/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, Hans
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mail-archive.com/ntg-context@ntg.nl/msg90783.html&#34;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; the
prerelease of a new version of ConTeXt called LuaMetapostTeX or LMTX for short.
LMTX is supposed to a streamlined and stripped down version of LuaTeX where
most of the backend code for writing PDF and images has been removed from the
engine and is handled by macro package using Lua code. Some of the rationale
for the change in discussed &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mail-archive.com/ntg-context@ntg.nl/msg90917.html&#34;&gt;in this
post&lt;/a&gt; and more
details including the source code and documentation will be available when
LMTX will be formally released in this year&amp;rsquo;s ConTeXt meeting. Currently just
the binary is available for testing from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pragma-ade.nl/install.htm&#34;&gt;Pragma Ade&amp;rsquo;s
website&lt;/a&gt;. There is no change in
user-facing code, so in principle, one can simply switch from ConTeXt MkIV to
LMTX without making any change in the tex file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my tests so far, I could compile all my documents using LMTX without any
noticeable difference. Nonetheless, I want to keep ConTeXt MkIV around for
some critical projects like typesetting material for courses that I teach.
In this post, I&amp;rsquo;ll explain my setup for using ConTeXt MkIV and LMTX in
parallel.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Frame With Solid Left Line Redux</title>
      <link>https://adityam.github.io/context-blog/post/frame-with-solid-left-line-redux/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2019 12:07:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adityam.github.io/context-blog/post/frame-with-solid-left-line-redux/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As I had &lt;a href=&#34;../frame-with-solid-left-line&#34;&gt;posted earlier&lt;/a&gt;, I like the visual
effect of placing a solid line on the left side of a block:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img class=&#34;center&#34;
  alt=&#34;Simple example&#34;
  src=&#34;https://adityam.github.io/context-blog/context-blog/post/frame-with-solid-left-line/leftframe-0.png&#34; /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I use this for displaying short code snippets in the lecture notes of a course
that I teach. Typically these are a few lines of Matlab code but recently I
needed to post a bigger code snippet where the frame should break across the
page. In principle, this should have been a simple change—replace the &lt;code&gt;framed&lt;/code&gt;
with a &lt;code&gt;textbackground&lt;/code&gt;—but that did not work out of the box. This blog post
explains a simple solution.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Speeding up PGFPlots using LuaTeX</title>
      <link>https://adityam.github.io/context-blog/post/speeding-pgfplot-using-luatex/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adityam.github.io/context-blog/post/speeding-pgfplot-using-luatex/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&#34;../metapost-vs-tikz-speed&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I compared the speed of
Metapost and TikZ for drawing similar graphics and found that &lt;strong&gt;TikZ is three
to five times slower than Metapost&lt;/strong&gt;. Although TikZ is slower, it does provide
a much higher level interface to drawing graphics and shifting to Metapost can
take a lot of &lt;em&gt;user time&lt;/em&gt;, which is often more valuable than &lt;em&gt;computer time&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example, consider the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ctan.org/pkg/pgfplots&#34;&gt;PGFPlots&lt;/a&gt; package, which provides a high-level
interface for drawing function plots. Although there is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/contextgarden/context-mirror/blob/beta/metapost/context/base/mpiv/mp-grap.mpiv&#34;&gt;Metapost package
for drawing
graphs&lt;/a&gt;, PGFPlots has more features and better documentation. In this post, I show that we can speed up plotting functions using PGFPlots by offloading the function computation to LuaTeX.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparing the speed of Metapost and TikZ</title>
      <link>https://adityam.github.io/context-blog/post/metapost-vs-tikz-speed/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adityam.github.io/context-blog/post/metapost-vs-tikz-speed/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a frequent user of both Metapost and TikZ, I often observe that TikZ is
considerably slower than Metapost. But what&amp;rsquo;s the actual difference in speed?
Let&amp;rsquo;s consider basic operations: drawing straight lines and drawing circles.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Externalizing Metapost graphics</title>
      <link>https://adityam.github.io/context-blog/post/externalizing-metapost/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adityam.github.io/context-blog/post/externalizing-metapost/</guid>
      <description>TikZ has a library external that converts a TikZ picture to a separate PDF. The TikZ documentation provides three reasons of why external images are useful:
 Compiling large images takes a lot of time. However, most images do not change from run to run. So, it can save time to export finished images and include them as external figures. Sometimes, it is desirable to have separate graphics, for example to include them in third party programs (think XHTML export).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>